Guide to the Mailliard Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Mailliard Family papers
1785-1896
MS 341
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4.5
(8 boxes, 1 folio)
The major part of these papers consist of correspondence, business papers and memorabilia relating to Joseph Bonaparte, ex-king of Naples and Spain. These were accumulated by Louis Hypolite Mailliard who acted as secretary to Bonaparte and was later executor of his estate. Most of these papers related to the affairs of the estate, including property in Bordentown, New Jersey, where Napoleon lived in exile from 1816 to 1839. A small amount of the correspondence as well as journals kept by Louis Mailliard from 1835-1844 concern Napoleon's personal affairs. Other members of the Bonaparte family figure in the correspondence as well since the Mailliard family acted as executor for them also. Included in the papers is a small amount of miscellaneous correspondence (1839-1857) of George Sumner including letters from Washington Irving, Alexis de Tocqueville, Henry W. Longfellow, William H. Prescott and William E. Gladstone.
Mailliard family
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of J. Ward Mailliard, Jr., 1953.
Scope and Contents
The Mailliard Family Papers extend from 1785-1896, although most of the material falls within the period ca. 1817-1860.
The collection is in two parts, the first containing correspondence to George Sumner (1817-1863), a political economist born in Boston, educated in Europe and well acquainted with European affairs. Among those corresponding with him are statesmen, historians, and artists of France, England, and America. These include such names as Washington Irving, George Peabody, Henry W. Longfellow, William H. Prescott, William E. Gladstone, Alexis de Tocqueville and Robert C. Winthrop. This correspondence dates primarily from 1839-1857. The collection also contains a number of letters addressed to others from such persons as Oscar Wilde, Edward S. Gould, Ernest W. Longfellow, and Thomas A. Edison. Besides correspondence, this section contains some printed biographies of members of the Ward family of Rhode Island.
The remainder of the collection concerns Joseph Bonaparte (1768-1844), ex-king of Naples and Spain (known as the Count of Survilliers after 1815), and other members of the Bonaparte family. These papers were accumulated by Louis Hypolite Mailliard (b.1795), who acted as secretary to Bonaparte and later served as executor of his estate. Mailliard was assisted in his duties as executor by his son Adolph Mailliard (b.1819). The Mailliards were also appointed the executors of the wills of other members of the Bonaparte family subsequent to the death of Joseph Bonaparte.
A small part of the correspondence as well as a journal kept by Louis Mailliard relates to the personal affairs of Joseph Bonaparte. Most of the material, however, including correspondence, business and legal papers, and record books, covers the execution of Bonaparte's estate. A considerable amount of the material relates to the Bonaparte estate in Bordentown, New Jersey, where Joseph Bonaparte lived for some time while in exile in America.
The Mailliard Family Papers were donated to Yale University Library by J. Ward Mailliard, Jr. 1953.
Economics; Families; Bordentown (N.J.); Europe; France -- History -- 19th century; Middle Atlantic States; Rhode Island; Inventories; Joseph Bonaparte, King of Spain, 1768-1844; Bertin, Georges, b. 1849; Bonaparte, Charles Lucian, 1803-1857; Bonaparte, Joseph Lucien Charles Napoléon, 1824-1865; Bonaparte, Lucien Louis Joseph Napoléon, 1828-1895; Bonaparte, Napoléon Charles Grégoire Jacques Philippe, b. 1839; Bonaparte, Zénaide Charlotte Julie Bonaparte, 1802-1854; Chapman, Nathaniel, 1780-1853; Cotte, J. Charles; Crémieux, Adolphe, 1796-1880; Dubarry, Edmund S.; Edison, Thomas A. (Thomas Alva), 1847-1931; Gabrielli, Plaide; Gladstone, W. E. (William Ewart), 1809-1898; Gould, Edward Sherman, 1808-1885; Hopkinson, Joseph, 1770-1842; Irving, Washington, 1783-1859; La Coste, Emilie; Longfellow, Ernest Wadsworth, 1845-1921; Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth, 1807-1882; Mailliard, Louis Hypolite, b. 1795; Peabody, George, 1795-1869; Prescott, William Hickling, 1796-1859; Sumner, George, 1817-1863; Tocqueville, Alexis de, 1805-1859; Wilde, Oscar, 1854-1900; Winthrop, Robert C. (Robert Charles), 1809-1894; Mailliard family; Ward family
- Inventory, 1785-1896
  - Correspondence of George Sumner
    - 1839-1900, no date (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
  - Ward family of Rhode Island: biographical sketches and memorabilia, 1875-1882 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence of Joseph Bonaparte
    - 1785-1796, 1817-1828, 1830-1834, 1836-1856 (Box 2, Folder 8-28)
    - 1857-1869, 1872-1875, 1877-1883, 1890-1896, no date (Box 3, Folder 29-37)
  - Correspondence of Joseph Bonaparte and Baring Brothers
    - 1817-1855, no date (Box 4, Folder 38-50)
  - Business papers of Joseph Bonaparte
    - 1804-1847, 1849-1857, 1858-1865, 1870, no date (Box 5, Folder 51-71)
    - Notebook entitled "Memorandum-objets donnes ou vendus," relating to the property of Joseph Boanparte, 1831-1841 (Box 6, Folder 72)
    - "Introito eu Esito della Galleria a discarico per li S.S. Interessati", [1842-1844?] (Box 6, Folder 73)
    - Inventory of the estate of Joseph Bonaparte, 1844 (Box 6, Folder 74)
    - Receipts and expenses relating to the settlement of Joseph Bonaparte estate, 1844 (Box 6, Folder 75)
    - Account of Louis Mailliard, surviving executor of the estate of Joseph Bonaparte, 1844-1858 (Box 6, Folder 76)
    - "Copies des decrets de la chancellerie du New Jersey sur les affaires de L'hoirie du Comte de Survilliers... ", 1848-1851 (Box 6, Folder 77)
    - "List of certificates of Pennsylania 5 and 6 per cent loan, selected for the payment of the legacy...", 1849 (Box 6, Folder 78)
    - "Registre des valeurs appartenantes a L'hoirie de M. le Comptes de Survilliers", 1849-1853 (Box 6, Folder 79)
    - Notebook of stocks and comptes, 1849-1853 (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - Louis Mailliard
    - Journals of 1833-1835, 1840, 1841 (Box 7, Folder 80)
    - Journals of 1841-1842, 1843, 1843-1844 (Box 7, Folder 81)
    - Journal pages 1815-1869 (Box 7, Folder 82)
  - Miscellany
    - Photograph of Napoleon III, undated (Box 8, Folder 83)
    - Anne E. Mailliard: three stories about Joseph Bonaparte told by Adolph Mailliard and Louis H. Mailliard, undated (Box 8, Folder 84)
    - Genealogical notes, undated (Box 8, Folder 85)
    - Volume of manuscript poems and prose passages, undated (Box 8, Folder 86)
    - Two poems by Delille, undated (Box 8, Folder 86)
    - Biographie de Joseph-Napoleon Bonaparte, 1832 (Box 8, Folder 87)
    - Napoleon Buonaparte by General Sarazin, undated (Box 8, Folder 88)
    - Bulletin des Lois. No. 62. No. 561:"Statut réglant la condition et les obligations des membres de la Famille Imperiale", 1853 (Box 8, Folder 89)
    - Newspapers, 1844, 1853, 1855 (Box 8, Folder 90)
    - Engravings, undated (Box 8, Folder 91)
    - Translations of letters by J. Mailliard, undated (Box 8, Folder 92)
  - Business papers, 1816-1858 (Box 9)